好夜晚
编剧：史蒂文·莫法特
River 到安特卫普再见
River! I'll see you in Antwerp!
告诉玛丽莲她太迟了
Tell Marilyn she's too late,
必须坐双翼飞机过来了
she'll have to use the biplane.
保重
Take care.
你每天晚上都这么做吗
Do you do this every night?
你好
Hello.
你正尝试藏起一个中音号
You're trying to conceal a euphonium.
一副有罪的样子 你以前就经常这么干么
Guiltily. Has that ever been attempted before?
什么 这个啊 没错
What? Oh, this. Oh, yeah,
它就是一个普通的中音号
it's just one of those euphoniums.
好吧 所以我们晚上睡觉的时候 你就在干这个
Okay, so is this what you do at night when we're sleeping?
去经历更多的冒险
Have extra adventures?
我没有你们睡得时间长 我得找点事情做
I don't sleep as much as you. I keep busy.
忙着做些什么 这一次就告诉我吧
Doing what? Actually, tell me for once.
你是我的朋友
You're my friend,
我最好的朋友
my best friend.
告诉我你究竟都做些什么吧
So tell me what it is you do.
好吧 我刚帮助了月球基地里一个被附身的管弦乐队
Okay. I just helped out a possessed orchestra on a moon base.
在此之前 我阻止了两颗超新星爆发
Before that, I prevented two supernovas,
重写了宇宙的历史 都是开玩笑的
wrote a history of the universe, all in jokes,
还在布里克斯顿做了点临时代理的工作
and did a bit of locum work in Brixton.
有趣的业务 十分缺人手
Lovely practice, very short-staffed.
怎么了
What's wrong?
我们只是你生命中微不足道的一小部分 不是吗
We're all such tiny parts of your life, aren't we?
你的朋友们都来了又走 匆匆而过
All the friends you make just flicker in and out.
你肯定都注意不到我们
You must hardly notice us.
Amy
AMY
你们是我生命中很重要的部分
you are enormous parts of my life.
也是我唯一能留下的回忆
And you are all I ever remember.
说起这个
Speaking of which...
我的人生不合常理
My life doesn't make any sense.
我知道
I know.
这就是我一直想和你谈的
That's what I've been trying to talk to you about.
我知道
I know.
比如
Now,
当我第一次遇见你时 我没有父母
when I first met you, I didn't have parents.
我从来没有过父母
I never had parents.
然后在你做了所有那些事之后
And then you did whatever it was you did
你重启了宇宙 突然间…
and rebooted the universe and suddenly, I...
我有父母了
had parents.
而且我一直都有父母
And I've always had parents.
两种人生都在我的记忆里
And I remember both lives in my head,
两种记忆同时存在
both of them in my head at the same time.
这样挺好的不是吗
And it's fine, isn't it?
但是不应该是这样的
Yeah, but it shouldn't be.
为什么会挺好的呢
Why is it fine?
Rory 做了2000年的罗马人
Rory was a Roman for 2000 years.
他说他几乎不记得了
He says he hardly remembers it.
但是 有时你会发现他发呆凝望
Ah, but sometimes you catch him just staring.
Amy 关键是
The thing is, Amy,
每个人的记忆都是一团乱麻
everyone's memory is a mess.
生活本身就是一团乱麻
Life is a mess.
每人都会有那些记忆
Everyone's got memories
比如一场他们没有度过的假
of a holiday they couldn't have been on
或是他们从未参加的宴会
or a party they never went to,
或者与某人初次相遇
or met someone for the first time
却感到认识他们一辈子了
and felt like they've known them all their lives.
时间正在被重写 就在我们周围 就在每一天
Time is being rewritten all around us, every day.
人们觉得是自己的记忆不好
People think their memories are bad,
其实他们的记忆没问题
but their memories are fine.
过去真的就是这个样子的
The past is really like that.
这太荒谬了
That's ridiculous.
啊 你现在开始明白了
Yeah, now you're starting to get it.
把手放在那里
Put your hand here.
这是什么
What is it?
塔迪斯心灵感应电路
Tardis telepathic circuits.
我要做什么
What do I do?
什么都不用做 只要放松
Nothing, just relax.
你最悲伤的记忆是在一个露天马戏场 1994年
Your saddest ever memory was at a fairground in 1994.
你还记得是为什么吗
Can you remember why?
不记得 等等 是不是…
No. Hang on, did I...
我冰激凌掉地上了
Did I drop an ice cream?
这不可能是我最悲伤的回忆
That can't be my saddest memory.
冰激凌的记忆总是悲伤的
Remembering ice cream's always sad.
我们着陆了么 我们在哪儿
Did we just land? Where are we?
你冰激凌掉地上以后发生了什么
What happened after you dropped the ice cream?
什么都没有 我一直在哭
Nothing, I cried.
不对 等下 有一位女士
No, no, hang on. There was a lady.
她又给我买了一个
And she bought me another one.
她真好 她长什么样子
Good for her. What did she look like?
她看起来…
She looked like she...
她穿着滑稽的衣服 一件睡衣
She had a funny dress, a nightdress.
她长着红头发
She had red hair.
博士
Doctor...
我不明白
I don't understand.
你为什么要这么做 有什么意义呢
Why are you doing this? What is the point?
那位好心的女士她对你说了什么
The nice lady, what did she say to you?
开心点 享受你的冰激凌吧
Cheer up. Have an ice cream.
Amy 时间与空间从来都不符合什么常理
Amy, time and space is never ever going to make any kind of sense.
很久以前 你就得到了关于
A long time ago, you got
如何对待它的最好的建议
the best possible advice on how to deal with that.
所以 我建议
So, I suggest
你去给出这个建议
So, I suggest you go and give it.
等等 等等 我
Okay, okay, so I
问了你一个关于人生的重大问题
ask a big, important question about life
而你基本上就是告诉我
and you're basically telling me
去给自己买个冰激凌
to go and buy myself an ice cream.
不 Amy 我在告诉你
No, Amy, I am telling you
去给我们俩一人买一个
to go and buy us both ice creams.
我超爱露天马戏场
I love fairgrounds.
我讨厌你
I hate you.
你才不会呢
No, you don't.
你坐幽灵列车的时候会害怕么 我有点怕
Do you get scared on ghost trains? I get a bit scared.
所以我能不能抓着你的手呢
So is it okay if I hold your hand?